So we need to do policy iteration so shall
we are, should we not when we started late
I know it's my mistake here oh okay, so that
leaves us with 15 minutes I think, we could
do it in 15 minutes, so policy ration the
idea is very simple, right so I start off
with some arbitrary policy let us say p0 may
start off with some arbitrary policy p0 I
find weep I not, right then what do, I do
I be greedy with respect to vp0 I will find
p1 right.
.
So being greedy is this right so I will take
some p0 solve fine vp0, right then do this
and I will find p1, right and then I find
vp1 plug that backend here right, so essentially
I will plug in VN here find pn+1 right, so
keep going until I converge and convergence
here is more straight forward if you stay
with the same policy you converge where unusually
convergence is much faster the rate of convergence
much faster with policy, iteration but, for
variety of reasons value iteration remains
a very favorite algorithm for many war people
don’t like policy iterations for, some reasons.
So but people get the idea for the policy
iteration is right you can go implement policy
patients rather easy, right so first so let's
of arbitrary sorry I hate going back and forth
select an arbitrary p0, right second step
is called, policy evaluation so where you
say, refined vp0 right so policy evaluation
is just find vpn right so we can just do this
by solving the system of equations I can just
take the inverter inversion in the inverse
of that matrix and solve it right or if you
like it you could do the iterative fashion
just just like you did in value iteration
instead of iterating on L I can iterate on
lp, right and then I let have some stopping
criterion for stopping it but I can do this
as well next thing is called policy.
.
Policy improvement okay this is a second step
is called policy evaluation third step is
called policy improvement, just like we mentioned
earlier it says mark Maxes then component-wise,
right for every state yes you do the max,
it is whatever I wrote here before erased
it at the beginning at exactly that, only
difference is here I am plugging in vpn it
is not V* right so this vpn and I do this
argmax over p and at every step because I
am checking for equality for stopping right.
So there could be multiple actions that give
you the max here right, so if at step n you
chose an action for giving a max like step
n there is some action your chosen as policy
for a state s in step n+1 if the same action
belongs to the max set you will pick that
actually you do not pick an arbitrary action
from the maxim, suppose let us say going up
and going right right both are optimal, right
but in the previous step I had chosen going
up for the state this step I should chose
I should choose going up also in otherwise
I will just keep oscillating between up and
right up and right I might not figure out
that I have stopped right.
So I shouldn't choose an action from the maximizes
randomly right are arbitrarily I have to have
some mechanism by which I consistently break
ties so that, policies do not change when
they do not have to, pn+1 =pn stop and declare
that pn is 5* otherwise go too, well otherwise
increment n and go to step 2, right so it’s
rather easy, right so if the stopping condition
holds can you see why pn should be p*, that
doesn't mean anything it just means it’s
a fixed point, ypn should be p* well it is
a fixed point but it is a fixed point of L.
If you think about it max over p rp+?ppvp
ray that operation that looks like L that
is yell operating on vp then if I get that
p in the same beep I same p again, right so
that means the value function hasn't changed,
right so that means V=lv, so that means it
is the optimal value function right so if
pn=pn+1, because of the way I am generating
the sequence of p and if pn=pn+ 1 then pn
is p*, also I haven’t changed right because
the apology has it changes the value function
will interchange fiesta no because of the
way we are generating here right remain so.
So if the value function hasn’t changed
and this is essentially this part of it is
essentially L operating on vp and it does
not change so that essentially means, that
it is the optimal value function, okay and
what else do we need to show I said if pn=pn+1
then pn is V* pn is a p* by the way right
,what else we have to show, that I have to
show that happens right I will have to show
that that happens so we will do that in two
ways one we will have to show that so vpn+1
= vpn, right.
So why is that why you think that will be
greater, so basically pn+1 is a greedy policy
according to be pn, okay so taken vpn and
action greedily with respect to it and I get
pn+1, so that is what I mean like pn+1 satisfy
3 then, right this is clear right so because
pn+1 satisfies 3 so that is being greedy with
respect to vn well pn is some arbitrary policy
which is the same as this then that will give
the same answer otherwise this will be greater,
because this is the one obtained by maximizing
this expression, wait I took this expression
I am maximizing it and whatever gives me the
maximum I am saying is pn+1, right.
So this is the maximum on the left hand side
so the maximum has to be greater than or equal
to whatever value I will get by plugging in
some other pn here because this is the max
okay this is clear right one more step, so
I can say so why can I say this because this
is actually equal to vn that the right hand
side will be equal to vpn because it's a fixed
point of lp, so this is lp operating the lpn
operating on vpn such a fixed-point so this
is vpn so essentially this is it and if I
multiply both sides by, what do I get so that
into this is what, right.
So every step I will keep improving okay so
the last bit we need is to show that, there
are only a finite number of policies that
you can search through, if you are having
a finite MDP finite number of deterministic
policies we are searching through only deterministic
policies here, only finite a number of deterministic
policies you can search through if you have
a finite MDP so that is basic approved it
so policy iteration will converge, but every
time I have to become better and there are
only finite number of things I can search
through at some point so I 'll have to stop,
or is it okay the component ways so every
component, of v is greater than sorry I didn't
define it earlier I should have so this essentially
means set vn+1 of s1 is greater than or equal
to v1 of s1 of s2 s3 for all s, right I think
there are people clamoring to come in so that's
why I stopped we can go out and you can ask
questions.